Finding Aid for Eric R. Wolf Papers, 1939-2011
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Eric R. Wolf papers 1939-2011
Wolf, Eric R., 1923-1999.
1 oversize folders
14 linear feet
02154 Aa 2; Ac
Anthropologist; professor of anthropology at the University of Michigan and the City University of New York. The collection is organized into eight series: Biographical; Correspondence; Fieldwork; Courses; Lectures; Publications; Graduate school and other notes; and Political activities.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Sydel Silverman (Donor No. 9078 ) and came to the library in multiple accessions beginning in 2001.
The collection is open to research.
Anthropologist Eric Wolf is known for having brought a historical perspective into the field of anthropology, integrating also prehistory, ethnohistory, and ethnology into his writings. He explored the topics of ethnicity and ecology, and his book Peasants (1966), established the topic as one for international and interdisciplinary research.
Born in Vienna in 1923, Eric Wolf grew up in the midst of radical changes throughout Europe. In 1933, his family moved to the Sudetenland, where his father was a manager for a textile factory and where interethnic conflict had been exacerbated by the rise of Nazism. In 1938, after the German army occupied Austria, Wolf was sent to England, where he was rounded up in 1940 and sent to an internment camp near Liverpool. In 1940, the Wolf family escaped from England to the United States, settling in Queens, New York.
After serving in the U.S. Army's Tenth Mountain Division in World War II, Wolf graduated from Queens College in 1946 and entered the Ph.D. program at Columbia University that fall. There, Wolf and his cohort -- including, Sidney Mintz, Morton Fried, Elman Service, Stanley Diamond, Daniel McCall, Robert Manners, Rufus Mathewson, and John Murra -- formed the Mundial Upheaval Society, a group interested in expanding the boundaries of anthropology, and with many of whom he maintained contact over his lifetime.
Wolf received his doctorate from Columbia in 1951, and after a number of short teaching appointments, including positions at the University of Illinois, the University of Virginia, Yale University, and the University of Chicago, Wolf taught in the University of Michigan's Anthropology Department from 1961 to 1971, where he served as chair for two years. He left the University of Michigan for the City University of New York's Graduate Center, where he taught until his retirement in 1992.
As students, Wolf and Sidney Mintz conducted fieldwork Puerto Rico as part of Julian Steward's Puerto Rico Project, the beginning of a lifelong friendship. Also during his graduate school years, Wolf worked on Ruth Benedict's Research in Contemporary Cultures Project, interviewing Austrians in the New York City area.
In the 1950s, Wolf received several research grants, allowing him to conduct fieldwork in Mexico, resulting in the publication of his first book Sons of the Shaking Earth in 1959. In the 1960s, Wolf and his student John W. Cole conducted fieldwork in the Italian alpine towns of St. Felix and Tret, leading to the publication of The Hidden Frontier: Ecology and Ethnicity in an Alpine Valley in 1974.
Other noteworthy books written by Wolf include Europe and the People without History (1982), and Envisioning Power: Ideologies of Dominance and Crisis (1999).
As a lecturer, Wolf was in demand throughout his lifetime. He received a number of awards, including a MacArthur Foundation "genius grant" in 1990, and a number of honorary degrees.
Wolf passed away on March 6, 1999 at age 76. At the time of his death, he had just completed Pathways of Power: Building an Anthropology of the Modern World, which was published in 2001.
The Eric Wolf papers include notes and analysis related to his anthropological fieldwork, personal and professional correspondence, as well as course and lecture materials, documenting the many aspects of Wolf's professional life as an anthropologist, instructor, and mentor. The collection is organized into ten series: Biographical, Correspondence, Fieldwork, Early/Unpublished Writing, Courses, Lectures, Publications, Notes, Political Activities, and Other Materials.
Subjects:
Wolf, Eric R., 1923-1999.; Anthropologists--United States.; Anthropology--Study and teaching.; City University of New York--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Anthropology.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Wolf, Eric R., 1923-1999.; Ghani, Ashraf.
Genre Terms:
Videotapes.
- Biographical
  The Biographical series, 1939-1999 (1 linear ft.), consists of materials related to Wolf's life, including his curriculum vitae, a number of interviews in which he reflected on his life and work as an anthropologist, documentation related to a number of honors and awards he received, and professional involvement. These materials provide an introduction to Eric Wolf as well as the scope of his work.
  - Curriculum vitae circa 1999 (Box 1)
  - Awards
    - American Anthropological Association, Session in Honor of Eric Wolf 1990 (Box 1)
    - Balzan Prizes 1997 (Box 1)
    - Premio Internazionale di Etnografia Alpina, "Michelangelo Mariani," 1996 (Box 1)
    - Queens College, Honorary Doctor of Humane Letters 1998 (Box 1)
    - Session in Honor of Eric Wolf, AAA 1990 (Box 1)
    - School of American Research, J.I. Staley Prize 1988 (Box 1)
    - University of Amsterdam, Honorary Doctorate 1997 (Box 1)
    - University of Michigan, Honorary Doctor of Laws 1991-1992 (Box 1)
    - University of Vienna, Doctor honoris causa 1993 (Box 1)
  - Certificates: American Academy of Arts and Sciences, Certificate of Fellowship 1986 and National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America, Certificate of Membership, 1995 (Folder 1)
  - Collected Mementos 1995, undated (Folder 1)
  - Education
    - Columbia University Courses circa 1946-1951 (Box 1)
    - Columbia University Department of Anthropology Guide to the Literature 1947, 1949 (Box 1)
    - Columbia University Ph.D. Dissertation 1951 (Box 1)
    - Contemporary History Project, Oral History Sampler of the Ann Arbor Anti-War Movement 1981 (Box 1)
    - Early Course Reading Lists by MUS Members 1951-1958 (Box 1)
    - Graduate School Papers (Written for courses and for MUS) 1946-1947 (Box 1)
    - Marxism Notes 1939-1945 (Box 1)
    - Mundial Upheaval Society (MUS) study outline and letters 1950, 1987, 1994 (Box 1)
    - Queens College, Anthropology I, Fall 1941 (Box 1)
    - Seminar on Plantation Systems of the New World; Program, Participants, Photographs 1957 (Box 1)
  - Interviews
    - 1986, Ashraf Gahni, American Ethnologist (Box 1)
    - 1987
      - Ashraf Ghani, (1 VHS tape (Box 1)
      - Jonathan Friedman Current Anthropology (Box 1)
    - 1990 Mark Warhaft, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1993 Jaro Stacul, La Ricerca Folklorica (Box 1)
    - 1997 Erich Landsteiner and Reinhard Johler, Österreichische Zeitschrift für Geschichtswissenshaften (Box 1)
    - 1998 Gustavo Lins Ribeiro, Mana (Box 1)
    - 1998 Gerd Baumann, European Association of Social Anthropologists Newsletter (Box 1)
    - 1999 Gerd Baumann, European Association of Social Anthropologists Newsletter (Box 1)
  - Memorial Comments
    - Funeral 1999 (Box 1)
    - Roseberry at Eric R. Wolf Memorial 1999 (Box 1)
    - American Museum of Natural History/New York and American Anthropological Association/Chicago 1999 (Box 1)
    - American Anthropological Association/New Orleans 2002 (Box 1)
  - Obituaries 1999 (Box 1)
  - Professional Activities
    - AAA Ethics Committee 1968-1970 (Box 1)
    - AAA Ethics Committee -- New York Book Review 1970-1971 (Box 1)
    - AAA Humanities Committee 1984 (Box 1)
    - Academic Visitor, London School of Economics 1970-1973 (Box 1)
    - Anthropology and the Mediterranean Conference Role of Robert Redfield, 1997 (Box 1)
    - Conference on Nicaraguan Constitutional Process 1986, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Critical Anthropology, International Board, 1972 (Box 1)
    - Dialectical Anthropology, Editorial Committee, 1976 (Box 1)
    - External Examiner, University of the West Indies 1976 (Box 1)
    - Guggenheim Fellowship application (unsuccessful) 1989 (Box 1)
    - MacArthur Foundation Fellow 1990 (Box 1)
    - National Academy of Science Fellowship 1995-1998 (Box 1)
    - National Endowment for the Humanities, Senior Fellowship 1975-1977 (Box 1)
    - Photographs
      - Valley of Mexico Seminar, 1972 and McConochie/ Mediterranean Project, 1969, 1974, 1983 (Box 1)
      - Peasants Seminar, Lucknow 1978, Bellagio, Italy, 1980, Socialist Scholars Conference, Paris, 1983 (Box 1)
    - Photographic Slides. Yale 1959-1960; Plantation Conference, 1958 (Box 1)
    - Sabbatical 1984-1986 (Box 1)
    - Social Science Research Council, Planning Meeting on Popular Religion in Latin America 1980 (Box 1)
  - Talk (autobiographical) at Yale 1984 (Box 1)
  - Timeline circa 1999 (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series, 1933-2011 (3.2 linear ft.), is divided into five subseries: Alphabetical, Chronological, Collected, Family, and Topical. This arrangement reflects the arrangement of the correspondence as Wolf used it, with the exception of the subseries Collected correspondence, which contains correspondence actively solicited by Wolf's wife after his death. It is unclear whether this correspondence is duplicated within Wolf's own alphabetical and chronological files. In some cases, it appears that correspondence was placed in Wolf's alphabetical and chronological files after his death. The researcher should note that the correspondence in the alpha files is not exhaustive of Wolf's correspondence with individuals and that additional correspondence may be contained in his chronological file. Similarly, correspondents not outlined in the alphabetical files may be included elsewhere in the chronological files. Of particular note is Wolf's correspondence with his parents, which was often written from the field and is of a more personal vein; as well as correspondence with fellow anthropologists Sidney Mintz, Roger McConochie, and Harald Prins. Correspondence received in the 2005 accession was blended into these categories as well.
  - Alphabetical
    - Alcalay, Glenn 1994 (Box 2)
    - Altamirano, Teofilo 1998 (Box 2)
    - Atencio, Jaime 1989 (Box 2)
    - Ballew, Tad 1997 (Box 2)
    - Bourgois, Philippe 1982-1997 (Box 2)
    - Burdick, John 1990-1997 (Box 2)
    - Caro, Edith Quinn 1993 (Box 2)
    - Chagnon, Napoleon (Box 2)
    - Choi, Soo 1990-1997 (Box 2)
    - Davis, Shelton 1982-1983 (Box 2)
    - Denich, Bette 1986-1990 (Box 2)
    - Dombrowski, Kirk 1992, 1998 (Box 2)
    - Ferradas, Carmen 1993 (Box 2)
    - Friedman, Jonathan (Box 2)
    - Friedrich, Paul (Box 2)
    - Gaillard, Gerald 1996-1998 (Box 2)
    - Garcia, Fernando 1992 (Box 2)
    - Gingrich, Andre 1992 (Box 2)
    - Grabowski, Christine 1994 (Box 2)
    - Greenberg, James 1994-1995 (Box 2)
    - Grew, Raymond 1971-1972, 1993, 1996 (Box 2)
    - Grunenfelder-Elliker, Barbara 1991-1996 (Box 2)
    - Halbmeyer, Ernst 1998 (Box 2)
    - Hall, Gwendolyn 1988 (Box 2)
    - Hammar, Lawrence 1996 (Box 2)
    - Hansen, Elizabeth 1989 (Box 2)
    - Harris, Yolanda 1992 (Box 2)
    - Hauschild, Thomas 1998 (Box 2)
    - Hay, Michelle (Box 2)
    - Heyman, Josiah 1992-1999 (Box 2)
    - Higginson, John 1990-1999 (Box 2)
    - Holwitz, Stanley 1998 (Box 2)
    - Hune, Shirley 1992 (Box 2)
    - Iszaevich, Abraham 1974-1983 (Box 2)
    - Ishikawa, Noboru 1992-1996 (Box 2)
    - Jacopin, Pierre-Yves 1982-1987 (Box 2)
    - Johnson, Derek 1996 (Box 2)
    - Khan, Aisha 1987-1997 (Box 2)
    - Lauria-Perricelli, Antonio 1985-1995 (Box 2)
    - La Lone, Darrell 1992 (Box 2)
    - Lang, James 1997 (Box 2)
    - Linke, Uli 1989-1991 (Box 2)
    - Llanusa-Cestero, Renee 1990-1995 (Box 2)
    - Lopez, Ramonluis 1974 (Box 2)
    - Loyola, Luis 1984-1991 (Box 2)
    - Marschall, Wolfgang 1998 (Box 2)
    - Matwychuk, Margo 1986-1993 (Box 2)
    - Maynard, David 1997-1998 (Box 2)
    - McConochie, Roger 1979-1996 (scattered) (Box 2)
    - Medeiros, Carmen 1991 (Box 2)
    - Mintz, Sidney 1952-1965, 1990-1998, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Mitchell, William 1997 (Box 2)
    - Morales, Beatriz 1990-1991, 1996 (Box 2)
    - Musante, Patricia 1992-1994 (Box 2)
    - Navarra, Luca 1993 (Box 2)
    - Nemec, Thomas 1992-1996 (Box 2)
    - Neyzi Leyla 1985, 1992 (Box 2)
    - Nichamin, Julie 1986 (Box 2)
    - Nugent, David 1994-1998 (Box 2)
    - O'Connor, Geoffrey 1989-1991, 1996, 1998 (Box 2)
    - Orlove, Ben 1985-1989 (Box 2)
    - de Ortiz, Carol Meyers 1994 (Box 2)
    - Ortmayr, Norbert 1988 (Box 2)
    - Osmundsen, Lita 1976, 1986 (Box 2)
    - Park, Kyeyoung 1992-1997 (Box 2)
    - Perunovic, Sreca 1991-1997 (Box 2)
    - Price, Barbara 1996 (Box 2)
    - Prins, Harald 1980-1998 (Box 2)
    - Rappaport, Roy 1994 (Box 2)
    - Rashford, John 1976-1998 (scattered) (Box 2)
    - Rebel, Hermann 1988-1999 (Box 2)
    - Reyna, Steve 1992-1997 (Box 2)
    - Ribeiro, Gustavo Lins 1983-1997 (Box 2)
    - Rincon, G. 1992 (Box 2)
    - Roosevelt, Anna 1996 (Box 2)
    - Rosenfeld, Henry 1985 (Box 2)
    - Sayer, Derek 1985-1998 (scattered) (Box 2)
    - Schroder, Barbara 1991 (Box 2)
    - Seo, Youngmin (Box 2)
    - Shanin, Teodor 1974-1976, 1987, 1996-1997 (Box 2)
    - Skoggard, Ian 1995, 1999 (Box 2)
    - Smith, Sheldon 1986, 1993-1994 (Box 2)
    - Spencer, Frank 1991 (Box 2)
    - Stolcke, Verena 1992-1993 (Box 2)
    - Tarn, Nathaniel 1989 (Box 2)
    - Taylor, Peter 1988 (Box 2)
    - Totti, Xavier 1992 (Box 2)
    - Trapp, Werner 1996-1998 (Box 2)
    - Trouillot, Michel-Rolph 1994-1995 (Box 2)
    - Vallance, Theodore 1964 (Box 3)
    - Velez-Ibanez, Carlos 1997-1998 (Box 3)
    - Verderey, Katherine 1995 (Box 3)
    - Wacquant, Loic 1994 (Box 3)
    - Wahl, Lissie 1992-1997 (Box 3)
    - Walter, Catherine 1988-1994 (Box 3)
    - Watanabe, John 1999 (Box 3)
    - Waterston, Alisse 1992-1993 (Box 3)
    - Western, Richard 1992 (Box 3)
    - Wilson, Thomas 1990-1995 (Box 3)
    - Woodson, Drexel 1997-1998 (Box 3)
    - Wright, Pamela 1990-1991 (Box 3)
    - Yengoyan, Aram 1991-1998 (Box 3)
    - Yi, Jeong Duk 1993-1997 (Box 3)
    - Zamosc, Leon 1987 (Box 3)
  - Chronological
    - Pre-1970
      - A-D (Box 3)
      - E-G (Box 3)
      - H-K (Box 3)
      - L-M (Box 3)
      - P-R (Box 3)
      - S (Box 3)
      - T-W (Box 3)
    - 1971-1979
      - A-B (Box 3)
      - C-D (Box 3)
      - E-G (Box 3)
      - H-J (Box 3)
      - K-L (Box 3)
      - M (Box 3)
      - P-R (Box 3)
      - S-T (Box 3)
      - W (Box 3)
      - Y-Z (Box 3)
    - 1980-1989
      - A (Box 3)
      - B (Box 3)
      - C-D (Box 3)
      - E-G (Box 3)
      - H-J (Box 3)
      - K-L (Box 3)
      - M-N (Box 3)
      - O-P (Box 3)
      - R (Box 3)
      - S-T (Box 3)
      - U-V (Box 3)
      - W (Box 3)
      - Y (Box 3)
    - 1990-1999
      - A-B (Box 3)
      - C-D (Box 3)
      - E-F (Box 3)
      - G-J (Box 3)
      - K-L (Box 3)
      - M-O (Box 4)
      - P-R (Box 4)
      - S (Box 4)
      - T-V (Box 4)
      - W-Z (Box 4)
  - Collected
    - By Date
      - 1940s misc. authors (Box 4)
      - 1960s misc. authors (Box 4)
      - 1970s misc. authors (Box 4)
      - 1980s misc. authors (Box 4)
      - 1955-1956, 1965, 1974-1999 (scattered) (Box 4)
      - 1990s misc. authors, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - By Name
      - Bourgois, Philippe 1982-1988 (Box 4)
      - Christian, William 1968-1986 (scattered) (Box 4)
      - McConochie, Roger 1969-1997 (Box 4)
      - Mintz, Sidney 1952-1957, 1987-1998 (Box 4)
      - Mintz Sidney 1964-1965, 1985, 1990 (Box 4)
      - Nemec, Thomas 1964-1998 (scattered) (Box 4)
      - Petersen, Glenn 1995 (Box 4)
      - Prins, Harald 1982-1998 (Box 4)
      - Rebel, Hermann 1982-1999 (Box 4)
      - Redfield, Robert 1954-1958 (Box 4)
      - Rieger, Philipp 1973-1998 (Box 4)
      - Schneider, Jane and Peter 1965-1968 (Box 4)
      - Silverman, Sydel (about ERW) 1989-2010 (Box 4)
      - Silverman, Sydel (in reply to M. Warhaft) 1999-2000 (Box 4)
      - Wessman, James 1977-1985 (Box 4)
    - By Topic
      - Condolences from Professional Associates to Sydel Silverman 1999 (Box 4)
      - European Association of Social Anthropologists Conference, Frankfurt 1998 (Box 4)
      - Interview with Sydel Silverman by David Simon 2006 (Box 4)
      - Projects not reaching fruition 1971-1973, mid 1980s (Box 4)
      - Puerto Rico Project 1996, 1998, 2011 (Box 4)
      - Thailand Controversy within AAA 1966-1971 (Box 4)
  - Family
    - Kathleen and Eric Wolf, to Eric's Parents 1948-1968, 8 folders (Box 4)
    - Collected--to Father 1933 to Kathleen, 1960-1961; to David, 1989 from Peter Wolf, 1999 (Box 4)
  - Topical
    - Angel Palerm Festschrift 1982-1986 (Box 5)
    - Angel Palerm Prologue 1997-1998 (Box 5)
    - Applications 1949, 1951, 1959 (Box 5)
    - Awards and Honors 1973, 1986-1995 (scattered) (Box 5)
    - Department of European and Mediterranean Anthropology (EUROMED), Amsterdam 1990-1991 (Box 5)
    - Editing Error in Laura Nader's Contributed Essay to "The Cold War and the University" (1997) 1998-1999 (Box 5)
    - FBI Request 1980-1981 (Box 5)
    - Hidden Frontier Italian version and possibility of a German version, 1988-1996 (Box 5)
    - Highlander Folk School (during Summer 1941) 1993, 2002 (Box 5)
    - Invited Lectures and Presentations 1971-1982 (Box 5)
    - Journals and Publications
      - Comparative Studies in Society and History 1962-1965, 1973-1974, 1984-1998 (Box 5)
      - Critique of Anthropology 1986-1990 (Box 5)
      - Ethnohistory 1983-1989 (Box 5)
      - Ethnologia Europaea 1980-1989 (Box 5)
      - Historical Ecology 1996 (Box 5)
      - Journal of Historical Sociology 1984-1997 (Box 5)
      - School of American Research 1984, 1995 (Box 5)
      - Smithsonian Series in Ethnographic Inquiry 1984-1986, 1997 (Box 5)
      - Theory and Society 1978-1981, 1989-1992, 1997 (Box 5)
    - Lehman College 1974-1996 (scattered) (Box 5)
    - Morelos Conference and Michael MacDonald 1989, 1992 (Box 5)
    - Pathways of Power Pre-Publication Reviews, 1999 (Box 5)
    - Peasant Wars of the Twentieth Century-- Paperback Reprint Edition by University of Oklahoma Press, 1998-1999 (Box 5)
    - Proposal Evaluations, Book Reviews, Recommendations, etc. 1976-1998, 4 folders (Box 5)
    - Proposed Revision to Peasants Book with Sydel Silverman as Co-Editor, 1977-1978 (Box 5)
    - Puerto Rico Project 1948-1953, 1975 (Box 5)
    - Reply to Michael Taussig. 1987-1989 (Box 5)
    - Reviewer Comments on Europe and the People Without History, Pre-and Post-Publication, 1980-1986 (Box 5)
    - Scandinavian trip in 1984, 1980-1984 (Box 5)
    - Student Letters from the Field 1966 (Box 5)
- Fieldwork
  The Fieldwork series, 1947-1964 (2.0 linear ft.), consists of notes Wolf took in the conduct of his fieldwork in Puerto Rico, Italy, and as a part of Columbia University's Research in Contemporary Cultures project, as well as drawings, diagrams, and notes he created in analyzing his research. These papers provide evidence of Wolf's process and ongoing analysis as he conducted his fieldwork and prepared his findings.
  - Columbia University Research in Contemporary Cultures Project
    - Field Notes 1947, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Manual for Field Workers, 4 folders (Box 5)
  - Columbia University, Field Notes undated (Box 5)
  - Europe Photographs and Photographic Slides, 1960 (Box 5)
  - Italy -- St. Felix and Tret
    - Analysis
      - 1697 Document (Box 5)
      - Age of Marriage (Box 5)
      - Demographic Profile (Box 5)
      - Dispensations (Box 6)
      - Family History and Family Trees (Box 6)
      - Kinship Diagrams (Box 6)
      - Marriages (Box 6)
      - Marriages and Children (Box 6)
      - Marriage Locality Patterns (Box 6)
      - Marriages and Widowed Partners (Box 6)
      - Misc. Notes (Box 6)
      - Occupations other than Bauer (Box 6)
      - Sibling Sets (Box 6)
    - Family Histories, 16 folders (Box 6)
    - Field Notebook (Box 6)
    - Field Reports 1960-1961 (Box 6)
    - Guggenheim Fellowship Materials 1958-1960 (Box 6)
    - Journal Entries (Box 6)
    - National Science Foundation Proposal 1964 (Box 6)
    - Research Notes, Archives of Parish of St. Felix (Box 6)
    - Photographs (Box 6)
  - Mexico
    - Photograph and Photographic Slides, 1954-1956 (Box 7)
    - Photographic Slides 1968 (Box 7)
  - Puerto Rico
    - Analysis
      - Development and Functioning of the Family (Box 7)
      - Division of Authority and Labor (Box 7)
      - Socialization Process (Box 7)
      - Miscellaneous Notes and Charts, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Field Notes
      - March-December 1948, 10 folders (Box 7)
      - January-March 1949 July-August 1949, 4 folders (Box 7)
    - Illustrated Song Book for Christmas 1950 (Box 7)
    - Photographs, 1947-1948 and 35mm film, undated (Box 7)
    - Photographs, Topographical (Box 7)
- Early/Unpublished Writing
  The Early/Unpublished Writing series, 1951-1998 (0.8 linear ft.), contains materials received in the fourth accession and added to the collection in 2011. Most of the items in this series date from the early years of Wolf's academic career. Just as the Publications series also contains some of Wolf's unpublished writing, the Early/Unpublished Writing series contains some of his published work as well as unpublished writings.
  - Writings on the Nation 1951-1952 (Box 7)
  - Honors Day Speech, University of Illinois 1953 (Box 7)
  - "Significance of Murdock's 'Social Structure'," Paper and Correspondence 1953 (Box 7)
  - Texcoco (Mexico) Project, with Aerial Photograph 1953-1954, 1956 (Box 7)
  - Project for Research on Cross-Cultural Regularities, Progress Reports 1954 (Box 7)
  - With Angel Palerm, "...Irrigation System near Texcoco Mexico," AAA 1954 (Box 7)
  - "The Community and the Nation in Mexico," Bloomington 1955 (Box 7)
  - Symposium on Cross-Cultural Regularities, University of Illinois 1955 (Box 7)
  - With Angel Palerm, "New Light on the Archaic in the Valley of Mexico," Paper, Correspondence, and Photographs 1956, 1960, 1992 (Box 7)
  - "Modern Races are Variations of the Same Species," Panel, Virginia Council on Human Relations 1956 (Box 7)
  - With Mort Fried, Hypotheses on Bilateral Societies 1959 (Box 7)
  - "Political Themes," Notes/Paper Presented at the AAA, Mexico City Undated (Box 7)
  - Research Proposals to Study Culture Change, Plans and Correspondence 1955-1959 (Box 7)
  - NSF-funded Conference to Plan Coordinated Anthropological Research in the Valley of Mexico 1960 (Box 7)
  - Introduction to the National Teach-In on the Vietnam War, Washington, DC 1965 (Box 7)
  - Wenner-Gren Conference, "Anthropological Horizons," with correspondence from Claude Levi-Strauss 1960-1961 (Box 7)
  - Wenner-Gren Conference, "The Evolutionist Interpretation of Culture," organized by Wolf 1964-1965 (Box 7)
  - University of Michigan Conference, "The Village and its Setting in the Mediterranean Area," Co-chaired by Wolf 1963 (Box 7)
  - Carnegie Seminar on Developing Nations, University of Indiana, "Peasants and Revolution," 1967 (Box 7)
  - Social Scholars Conference, New York City, "Peasant Problems and Revolutionary Warfare," 1967 (Box 7)
  - Notes and Commentaries on the Study of Culture 1958-1968 (Box 7)
  - Wenner-Gren Conference, "The Nature and Function of Anthropological Traditions," 1968 (Box 7)
  - Foreign Policy Group, University of Michigan, "US Policy and the 'Third World'," for Senator Philip Hart 1970 (Box 7)
  - Comments on Economic History and the Culture of Cities 1970-1972 (Box 7)
  - Lecture, Lehman College, City University of New York, "What is Vietnam?," 1972 (Box 7)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science Symposium, "Mode of Production," 1975 (Box 7)